<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>blog</title>
<link>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Post With Code</title>
  <dc:creator>Harlow Malloc</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/post-with-code/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is a post with executable code.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <category>analysis</category>
  <guid>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/post-with-code/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/post-with-code/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To My Blog</title>
  <dc:creator>Jake Bennett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Here is my first blog to test things out.</p>
<p><img src="https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/welcome/thumbnail.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Since this post doesn’t specify an explicit <code>image</code>, the first image in the post will be used in the listing page of posts.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Evaluating a Betting Stragey Based on The Athletic’s Projections</title>
  <dc:creator>Jake Bennett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>During the 2024-2025 NFL season, The Athletic maintained an NFL projections webpage [INSERT LINK HERE] that contained forecasts for each regular season and playoff game. Each projection included a forecasted points spread, and I was curious to see how these forecasts compared to the Las Vegas spreads and the actual game outcomes. I back-tested a simple betting strategy:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>When The Athletic’s spread is greater than the Vegas spread, bet on the favorite.</p></li>
<li><p>When The Athletic’s spread is less than the Vegas spread, bet on the underdog.</p></li>
<li><p>If the spreads are the same, do not place a bet.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The strategy only makes spread bets (i.e., no moneyline bets), and assumes -110 odds (wagering $110 to win $100).</p>
<p>Of the 285 NFL games in the 2024-2025 season (regular season and playoffs), there were 238 games where The Athletic’s spread did not match the Vegas spread. On average, The Athletic’s spread differed from the actual game out come by 9.75 points, while Vegas’ spread differed by 9.66 points. The median differences for The Athletic and Vegas were 7.5 points and 7 points, respectively. These are minimal differences, to be sure, but the Vegas lines were more accurate for the 2024-2025 season.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the betting strategy described above does not give us an edge. Assuming bets of $110, employing the strategy would have lost $1,460 for a return of -5.58%. In fact, using the complete opposite strategy would have lost $830 for a return of -3.17%, which is less than the -4.55% we would expect from winning half of our bets. [Insert thing about confidence interval here]</p>
<p>Then I wondered if The Athletic’s spread forecasts were better for a particular direction. That is to say, what if we bet only on games where The Athletic had the favorite favored by more? What if we bet only on games where The Athletic had the favorite favored by less?</p>
<p>It turns out that betting only on games where The Athletic had the favorite favored by more than Vegas would have been profitable to varying degrees, depending on what threshold of spread difference is used.</p>
<p><img src="https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/images/clipboard-1410853896.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The same cannot be said for games where The Athletic has the favorite favored by less:</p>
<p><img src="https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/images/clipboard-1410853896.png" class="img-fluid"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>NFL</category>
  <category>sports</category>
  <guid>https://jake-p-bennett.github.io/blog/posts/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 22:09:12 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
